{"tossups": [{"question": "An orphan's attempt to find two parents who disappeared in this country is the subject of the novel <em>When We Were Orphans</em>. Military conflict in this country also affects Jim Graham, a British child living here in J.G. Ballard's novel <em>Empire of the Sun</em>. This country's classic literature includes <em>Journey to the West</em> and <em>The Dream of the Red Chamber</em>. For the point, name this country whose <em>Romance of the Three Kingdoms</em> describes the fall of the Han Dynasty.", "answer": "<b><u>China</u></b> [or People's Republic of <b><u>China</u></b>, etc.; no one formal name applies to all periods referenced in the question]", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This country's independence revolt was triggered by a performance of the opera <em>The Mute Girl</em> <em>of Portici</em> (<b>pr. por-TEE-chee</b>). This country\u2019s region of Wallonia was the first in continental Europe to industrialize. This country has often suffered political gridlock due to conflicts between its French and Flemish speakers. For the point, name this low country, whose ghoulish king Leopold II exercised personal rule over its namesake Congo.", "answer": "<b><u>Belgium</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "A powerful patron of this movement helped spark it by arresting the Guangxu (<b>pr. gwong-SHOO</b>) Emperor. The Eight-Nation Alliance was sent to put down this movement, which resisted modernization efforts exemplified by the recent Hundred Days and Self-Strengthening movements. This movement was supported by Dowager Empress Cixi (<b>pr.SEE-shee</b>) and believed itself invulnerable to bullets. For the point, name this 1898 anti-foreigner uprising in China.", "answer": "<b><u>Boxer Rebellion</u></b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This composer conducted an 1829 performance of J.S. Bach's <em>St. Matthew's Passion</em> which revived Bach's reputation. Under the Nazis, Carl Orff was commissioned to replace this composer's incidental music to <em>A Midsummer Night's Dream</em>. Richard Wagner (<b>pr.VOG-nurr</b>) threw his gloves on the floor after conducting music by this composer. For the point, name this German Jewish composer of the <em>Scottish Symphony</em> and a widely used \"Wedding March.\"", "answer": "Felix <b><u>Mendelssohn</u></b> [Jakob Ludwig Felix <b><u>Mendelssohn</u></b> Bartholdy]", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {"question": "This man's credo of \"an honest day's pay for an honest day's work\" led him to lure employees to his factories by paying a then-unheard of five dollars a day. He also quipped that his customers could have his product in \"any color they want, as long as it's black.\" For the point, name this entrepreneur of the Model A and Model T, automobiles from the company bearing his name.", "answer": "Henry <b><u>Ford</u></b>", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "A battle named for this substance involved Alexander Nevsky turning back the Teutonic Knights at Lake Peipus. At Austerlitz, Napoleon ordered his artillery corps to shoot not at enemy soldiers but at this substance. This substance was stored in special \"houses\" during the early twentieth century to preserve food. For the point, name this substance which gives its name to an \"age\" that ended about twelve thousand years ago with the retreat of glaciers.", "answer": "<b><u>ice</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This scientist's name was briefly used to denote a fundamental force he explained, which is now known as the weak nuclear force. This first person to explain beta decay collaborated with Paul Dirac on a set of statistical mechanics equations. This physicist supervised Chicago Pile-1, the first man-made self-sustaining nuclear chain reaction. For the point, name this Italian-born member of the Manhattan Project.", "answer": "Enrico <b><u>Fermi</u></b>", "metadata": "Science - Physics"}, {"question": "Wolfe Tone led an unsuccessful rebellion in what is now this country, and this modern-day country is where the Croke Park massacre was perpetrated by the Black and Tans. Roger Casement and Patrick Pearse (<b>pr. PURSE</b>) were major leaders of the Easter Rising, which failed to secure the independence of this country. For the point, name this country which finally won independence thanks to the efforts of Sinn Fein (<b>pr. SHIN FAIN</b>) against Britain.", "answer": "Republic of <b><u>Ireland</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This man kept the outbreak of the Yom Kippur War a secret from the President for almost four hours, in order to begin his \"shuttle diplomacy\" plan. This man's joint receipt of the Nobel Peace Prize with Le Duc Tho allegedly inspired Tom Lehrer to quit comedy. He promoted \"Vietnamization\" and the opening of relations with China during his eight years under Nixon and Ford. For the point, name this German-born National Security Advisor and Secretary of State.", "answer": "Henry <b><u>Kissinger</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "William Claiborne was appointed to administer the territorial transfer caused by this action, which was negotiated by Robert Livingston. Contemporary commentators doubted the President's authority to perform this action, which cost only fifteen million dollars. It provided funds to Napoleonic France in exchange for doubling the size of the United States. For the point, name this 1803 action by which Thomas Jefferson acquired what is now the Midwest.", "answer": "<b><u>Louisiana Purchase</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This man invoked an Aeschylus (<b>pr. ESK-uh-liss</b>) quote about \"wisdom through the awful grace of God\" while standing in the bed of a truck in Indianapolis, where he prevented rioting by announcing the death of Martin Luther King, Jr. He was himself killed two months later at the Ambassador Hotel by Sirhan Sirhan. For the point, name this Attorney General in his brother's administration and leading Democratic Presidential candidate prior to his death in 1968.", "answer": "<b><u>R</u></b>obert Francis <b><u>Kennedy</u></b> [or <b><u>RFK</u></b>; prompt on <b><u>Kennedy</u></b>]", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "John Hay replaced this man as Secretary of State. An act named for this man was neutered three years after its passing by the <em>E.C. Knight</em> case. This man names another 1890 act which required the federal government to prop up the falling value of coins by purchasing precious metals on a monthly basis. For the point, identify this namesake of a Silver Purchase Act and an Antitrust Act, a Senator from Ohio who was the brother of Civil War general William Tecumseh.", "answer": "John <b><u>Sherman</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Ed Delahanty, Rogers Hornsby, and Ty Cobb each performed this feat three times. The last MLB player to do this was Ted Williams, who refused to sit out a season-ending doubleheader to artificially protect this mark. The last serious challengers to this feat were George Brett in 1980 and Tony Gwynn, whose attempt at this mark in 1994 was cut short by the strike. For the point, identify this feat, not accomplished since 1941, in which a batting average milestone is achieved.", "answer": "hitting above.<b><u>400</u></b> in a season [or \"batting <b><u>four hundred</u></b>\", etc.]", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "This religion's founder was influenced by the patron of the Sant Mat religious movement, Kabir. This religion's members were targeted by rioters in 1984 after followers of this religion assassinated Indira Gandhi. This religion follows the \"Five Ks\" including the non-cutting of hair, which is instead worn in a turban. For the point, name this religion, originating in the Punjab (POON-job) region of north India, which was founded by Guru Nanak in the 1480s.", "answer": "<b><u>Sikh</u></b>ism", "metadata": "Religion - Religion"}, {"question": "Thomas Bloodworth was the governor of this city during a calamity that began here on Pudding Lane. This city is the subject of <em>A Journal of the Plague Year</em>, which fictionalizes the start of a calamitous period in this city that ended with it burning down and being rebuilt by Christopher Wren. For the point, name this city which suffered a bubonic plague outbreak and its \"Great Fire\" in the 1660s, during the restored reign of King Charles II.", "answer": "<b><u>London</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Zoologist George Steller joined this man's Second Kamchatka (<b>pr. kahm-CHOT-kuh</b>) Expedition. This man discovered the volcano Mount Saint Elias and met his end from scurvy in the Commander Islands. Though he did not spy the shore in 1728, he did see land on his second expedition in 1741. For the point, name this Danish-born explorer who sailed east for Russia and proved the extent of the strait between Siberia and Alaska that is now named for him.", "answer": "Vitus <b><u>Bering</u></b>", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "In 1979, this company became the first American chain to offer a salad bar. This company's confusing 1984 commercial in which it compared its competitors to the Soviet Union led to a revamping of its ad strategy behind Clara Peller, who said its popular catchphrase, \"Where the Beef?\" For the point, name this Dave Thomas-founded chain which offers Frostys and square hamburgers, and is named for Thomas's red-haired daughter.", "answer": "<b><u>Wendy's</u></b>", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "This country compromised its Cold War neutrality when it signed the YYA Treaty. This country had a dispute over child custody with Russia in the 2003 Anton scandal. Following the breach of the Mannerheim Line, this country fought the Continuation War and Winter War against the Soviet Union. For the point, name this country which expelled Nazi troops from its northern Lapland region in 1945.", "answer": "<b><u>Finland</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "The oldest program of this kind which is still maintained is Lynx, which does not support any graphics. The \"bundling\" of a program of this kind was at the center of the antitrust lawsuit against Microsoft. The first program of this kind was written at CERN in January 1992 by Tim Berners-Lee. In the 1990s, popular programs of this kind included Mosaic and Netscape. For the point, identify this type of computer program such as Firefox, Safari, or Chrome.", "answer": "<b><u>web browser</u></b>", "metadata": "Science - Other Science - Computer Science"}, {"question": "Roy Lichtenstein made a 1972 pop art parody of a \"still life\" with this object. A 1931 painting shows this object \"with calico roses.\" Arthur Rothstein moved one of these objects onto a road to obtain a more dramatic photo of the effects of the Dust Bowl. This object dominates a painting subtitled \"red, white, and blue\" that was made by Georgia O'Keeffe. For the point, name these objects frequently found in art of the American west and left behind when a bovine expires.", "answer": "<b><u>cow skull</u></b> [or equivalents; prompt on <b><u>skull</u></b>]", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "During the Maccabee Revolt, Eleazar Maccabeus was killed after destroying one of these weapons by running under it in an ill-thought-out scheme. These weapons were used to great effect by King Porus to intimidate the Macedonians at the Hydaspes River, and they were defeated by Scipio using trumpets. Hannibal famously brought these weapons over the Alps. For the point, name these largest available weapons in ancient warfare, which had tusks and trunks.", "answer": "war <b><u>elephant</u></b>s", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "A character on this show lamented that Neville Chamberlain \"would still give you half of Europe\" even if you held his head in a toilet. A character on this show attempted to one-up a victim of the <em>Andrea Doria</em> sinking to get an apartment. This show featured a gang of street toughs who adored President Martin van Buren and once attacked Kramer. For the point, name this 1990s NBC sitcom about four antisocial New Yorkers.", "answer": "<em><b><u>Seinfeld</u></b></em>", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "This philosopher was invited to write a constitution in 1792, leading to his tract <em>Considerations on the Government of Poland</em>. He explained his ideal system of education in <em>Emile</em> and identified the source of legitimate political power as \"the general will.\" This author of the <em>Discourse on Inequality</em> posited that \"man is born free but is everywhere in chains.\" For the point, name this radical French philosopher who penned <em>The Social Contract.</em>", "answer": "Jean-Jacques <b><u>Rousseau</u></b>", "metadata": "Philosophy - Philosophy"}, {"question": "This city is where al-Mustasim (<b>pr. moos-tah-SEEM</b>) was executed by being rolled up in a carpet and trampled to death. Earlier, this city was where Yahya the Barmakid served as vizier to Harun al-Rashid, and where the House of Wisdom was built. This city was sacked by Hulagu (<b>pr. hoo-LAH-goo</b>) Khan in 1258, causing the Tigris to run black with the ink of destroyed books. For the point, name this capital of the Abbasid Empire in what is now Iraq.", "answer": "<b><u>Baghdad</u></b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This term was coined by Sylvia Porter in 1951. Its causes were mainly found in the GI Bill, which caused a spike in both home ownership and in the number of people able to acquire college educations, leading to an unprecedented number of families choosing to have children at the same time. For the point, identify this post-World War II phenomenon which created a namesake American generation of Beatles fans and Vietnam protestors.", "answer": "the <b><u>Baby Boom</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This city is served by the Melrose Arch and Sandton City shopping malls, and it includes an area predominantly populated by those of Indian descent, Lenasia. In 2002, bombs from the Boeremag attempted to prevent the incorporation into this city of the place where a 1976 uprising occurred, Soweto. The Constitutional Court sits in this city, the largest in the world not on a river or body of water. For the point, name this most populous city in South Africa.", "answer": "<b><u>Johannesburg</u></b>", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "In 1919, this located is where the march of the May 4 Movement ended and shouted slogans against the Twenty-One Demands. Later, this location is where a papier-mache Goddess of Democracy was built and the unidentified \"Tank Man\" attempt to thwart a military crackdown on demonstrators who responded to the death of reformist Hu Yaobang. For the point, name this large plaza in Beijing where liberalization protests were suppressed in 1989.", "answer": "<b><u>Tiananmen</u></b> Square", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "Theodore Whitney and Asa Judah pushed for the \"central route\" plan for this project, whose \"Southern route\" proponents engineered the Gadsden Purchase. In 1869, a silver hammer was used to drive in a golden spike at Promontory Point, formally completing the union of the Central Pacific and Union Pacific into this structure. For the point, name this long-dreamed-of single transportation route across the United States by locomotive.", "answer": "<b><u>transcontinental railroad</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "John Clayton led the effort to preserve one of these structures, which was begun near Segedunum with a milecastle system aimed more at tax collection than military aims. A later structure of this type, which ran from the Firth of Forth to the Firth of Clyde, was the northernmost extent of Roman power. For the point, identify these two Scottish structures, named for Antoninus Pius and Hadrian respectively, which were not effective at keeping Picts out.", "answer": "Roman <b><u>wall</u></b>s", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "An Art Young cartoon depicts this man adulterating his large jug of \"monopoly whiskey\" with a seltzer bottle labeled \"a little competition.\" This man organized the merger that created General Electric, as well as the creation of the first billion-dollar company, U.S. Steel. For the point, name this financier of the 1900s whose company merged in 2000 with Chase Manhattan.", "answer": "J.P. <b><u>Morgan</u></b> [John Pierpont <b><u>Morgan</u></b>]  <b>NHBB C 2014-2015 </b> <b>Bee Round 3 </b> <b>Extra Question </b> <b>ONLY READ IF A MAKEUP FOR AN EARLIER QUESTION IS NEEDED </b> This author of the novels <em>The Fortified City</em> and <em>Zabibah and the King</em> consolidated his power upon the retirement of Ahmed Hassan al-Bakr by dramatically having accused traitors removed from a meeting one by one. This father of the notoriously dissolute Uday and Qusay was captured in Operation Red Dawn near his hometown of Tikrit, after which he was put on trial for ordering the Dujail Massacre. For the point, name this executed former dictator of Iraq.  ANSWER: Saddam <b><u>Hussein</u></b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}], "bonuses": []}